- This is the most dangerous problem in mathematics,
这是数学界最危险的课题
one that young mathematicians are warned not to waste their time on.
前人会告诫年轻的数学家  别把光阴浪费于此
It's a simple conjecture
这个猜想的描述十分简单
that not even the world's best mathematicians have been able to solve.
却连世界上最聪明的数学家也无法证明
Paul Erdős, a famous mathematician, said,
著名数学家Paul Erdős曾说过
当今的数学还没有成熟到能解决这种问题
Here's how it works.
这个猜想是这样的
Pick a number, any number.
选个数字  随便选哪个
Seven?
7？
Good choice.
好的
Okay, we're gonna apply two rules.
我们有两条规则
If the number is odd, we multiply by three and add one.
如果这是个奇数 把它乘3加1
So three times seven is 21, plus one is 22.
所以7乘3得21  加1得22
If the number is even, we divide by two.
如果是个偶数  那就把它除以2
So 22 divided by two is 11.
那么22除以2就得到了11
Now, we keep applying these two rules.
不断重复这两条规则
11 is odd, so we multiply by 3, 33, and add 1, 34.
11是奇数  ×3得33  +1得34
Even, divide by two, 17, odd.
这是偶数  ÷2得17  是奇数
Multiply by 3, 51, add 1, 52, even.
×3是51  +1得52  是偶数
Divide by two, 26, still even.
÷2得26  还是偶数
Divide by two, 13, odd.
÷2得13  是奇数
So we multiply by three, 39, add one, and that's 40,
于是我们×3得39  再+1得40
which is even, so we divide by two, 20,
这是偶数  于是÷2得20
divide by two, 10, divide by two, 5, odd.
再÷2得10  再÷2得5  奇数
Multiply by three, 15, add one, 16,
×3为15  再+1得到16
divide by two that's 8, and then 4, 2, and 1.
÷2得到8  一直下去是4, 2, 1
Now, 1 is odd, so we multiply by three and add one, which equals 4.
现在  1是奇数  所以我们把它×3+1得到4
But 4 goes to 2, goes to 1,
但4会变为2再变回1
so we're in a loop, and the lowest number is 1.
最后就在绕圈子了  最小的数是1
Now, the conjecture is this:
这个猜想是
every positive integer, if you apply these rules,
对于任意正整数  如果不断重复这两条规则
will eventually end up in the 4, 2, 1 loop.
最终都会进入 4-2-1 的循环
This is commonly called the Collatz conjecture after German mathematician, Luther Collatz,
这个猜想常被称为「考拉兹猜想」 得名于德国数学家卢瑟·考拉兹
who may have come up with it in the 1930s.
提出时间大约是20世纪30年代
But the problem has many origin stories and many names.
但这个猜想还被许多人分别独立地发现  因而得名颇多
It's also known as the
它也被称为
乌拉姆猜想
角谷猜想
思韦茨猜想
哈塞猜想
叙拉古猜想
and simply 3N+1.
或者干脆叫3N+1猜想
Why is 3x+1 so famous?
3X+1 问题为何如此著名
- Among professional mathematicians, maybe it's not famous but infamous,
它在职业数学家当中的确很知名——但是知的是恶名
in the sense that if someone actually admits in public that they're working on it,
大家公认  如果谁公开说自己在证明这个猜想
then there's something wrong with them.
那他肯定有猫病
- The numbers you get by applying 3x+1 are called
通过3x+1过程得到的数被称为
冰雹数
because they go up and down like hailstones in a thundercloud,
因为它们上上下下  好像雷雨云里的冰雹
but eventually, they all fall down to one,
但是它们最终统统都会落到1
or at least we think they do.
至少我们现在猜测是这样
You can think of the numbers as representing the height above the ground in meters.
你可以把这些数当成海拔高度
So a number like 26 would start 26 meters above the ground.
那么26这个数就表示海拔26米
And if you apply 3x+1, it rises up as high as 40 meters.
让它跑一遍3x+1  它最高会升到40米
And, in total, it takes 10 steps to get to one.
总共十步过后 它降到1米
So 10 is called its total stopping time.
因此  我们称它的停止用时为10
But take the very next number, 27,
而挨着26的数27
and it bounces around all over the place.
则一路上窜下跳
In fact, it climbs all the way up to 9,232.
它在落到底之前  最高冲到了9232米
As an altitude, that is higher than Mount Everest, before it too falls back to the ground.
把它当作高度的话 这比珠穆朗玛峰还高
In total, it takes 111 steps for 27 to get down to one
27这个数总共要111步才能掉到1
and end up in the four, two, one loop.
然后进入 4-2-1 的循环
The paths that different numbers take vary so widely,
即使是离得这么近的数
even numbers right next to each other.
它们的路径也相差甚远
So how do you even start to make progress on this problem?
所以  这问题有什么突破口吗
Well, honestly, mathematicians struggled.
说实在的  连数学家也难搞
- People just decided that
有些人说
this was something invented by the Soviets to slow down U.S. science,
这是苏联人发明的阴谋  用来阻碍美国的科学发展
警惕境外势力打数学牌
and it was doing a good job at it
而且这“阴谋”真的做到了
'cause everybody's sitting there, twiddling their thumbs
大把人都在掰着手指头研究这问题
and making no progress on this trivial thing that you can tell a school of children.
但在这个简单到小学生都听得懂的问题上  他们毫无进展
- Jeffrey Lagarias is the world authority on 3x+1.
在世界范围内  Jeffrey Lagarias是研究3x+1问题的权威
- The first time I met him I was a senior in college,
我读大四的时候第一次在大学里遇到他
and he pulled me aside and he said,
他把我拉到一边  他说
"Don't do this. Don't work on this problem.
快跑  别折腾这玩意
If you want to have a career,
如果你不想被同行鄙视  不想丢饭碗
do not start spending time writing about this
就别在这玩意上面浪费时间来写论文  发论文
or publishing any papers about this.
Do real math for a while to establish yourself."
花点时间去研究真正的数学  来打好你的基础
- Alex Kontorovich didn't listen.
Alex Kontorovich 并不听话
He and Yakov Sinai looked at the paths of the hailstone numbers.
他和 Yakov Sinai 观察了这些冰雹数的走势
Were there any patterns?
看看有没有什么规律
But obviously all of them ended up at one.
显然这些数最后都变成了1
But what about the paths they take to get there?
那么  变到1所走的路径呢
The pattern is randomness.
完全随机
Here is the sequence of a large number chosen at random.
我们任意选一个超大的数  图里展示了它的变化过程
The graph peaks and then drop so low
图像先冲到一个高峰  再掉得超低
that you can't really see what's happening at this scale.
低到在这个比例下根本看不出走势
But if you take the logarithm,
但是如果用对数比例
you find this wiggly graph with a downward trend.
你会看到这个一路蠕动下降的图
It looks like the stock market on a bad day.
就像你血本无归的基金
And this is no coincidence.
而且这不是巧合
Both are examples of geometric Brownian motion.
二者都是几何布朗运动的例子
That means if you take the log and remove the linear trend, the fluctuations are random.
意思是说 如果把它取对数之后放平  这些波动就是随机的了
It's like flipping a coin each step.
就像是每一步都抛硬币
If the coin is heads, the line goes up,
正面的话折线往上走
tails, it goes down.
反面就往下走
3x+1 is just like the random wiggles of the stock market.
3x+1 就好像是股市的波动
Over long-enough periods, the stock market tends to trend upwards,
只要时间足够长 （美国）股市趋向于上涨
while 3x+1 trends down.
而 3x+1 趋向于下降
Another way to analyze 3x+1
另一种分析 3x+1 的方式
is by looking at the leading digit of each number in a sequence.
是研究 3x+1 数列里各项的首位
Here are the hailstone numbers starting with three as the seed.
这里我们选取3作为初值  看看它的冰雹数列
And we can count up how many numbers start with a one,
然后统计有几个数的首位是1
how many start with a two,
几个数的首位是2
how many start with a three, and so on to make a histogram.
几个数的首位是3  以此类推  做出直方图
We can do the same thing for the sequence that starts with four, and that's a short one,
同样的  我们看始于4的数列  这就挺短的了
and for the sequences that start with five
接着看始于5的…
six,
接着看始于5的… 6的…
and seven.
接着看始于5的… 6的… 7的
Again, for each sequence,
对于各个冰雹数列
we're just counting up how many numbers start with each digit, 1 through 9,
按照首位是1-9来分别清点
and adding that to our histogram.
然后加到直方图里
If you keep doing this for more and more numbers,
只要统计的数越来越多
eventually the histogram settles into a stable pattern.
直方图最终会趋向于稳定的比例
For the first billion sequences,
对于前十亿项
you'll find one is by far the most common leading digit.
你会发现1是最常作为首位的数码
30% of all numbers start with one,
30%的数以1打头
around 17.5% start with two, 12% start with three,
17.5%以2打头  12%以3打头
and the frequency decreases for higher digits.
随着首位递增  其出现频率会递减
Fewer than 5% of all the numbers start with nine.
以9打头的数只占了不到5%
Now, this pattern is not unique to 3x+1.
这个规律并非是3x+1独有的
It actually comes up everywhere,
它其实会出现在许多领域
from the populations of countries,
从国家人口数
to the value of companies,
到公司价值
all the physical constants
物理常数
and the Fibonacci numbers, just to name a few.
乃至斐波那契数  不胜枚举
The distribution is known as Benford's law,
这个分布被称为「本福特   定律」
and it is even used to detect fraud.
它甚至能检测财务欺诈
If all the numbers on your income tax forms obey Benford's law,
如果你在税务申报表上的所有数值都符合这个定律
then, well, you're probably being honest.
那你应该是诚实的
If not, you may be hiding something.
没有的话  你是不是想搞事情
In elections, Benford's law can be used to spot irregularities,
在选举中  本福特定律也能用来发现异常
though you have to apply it correctly.
当然你得用对
Benford's law works best when the numbers involved span several orders of magnitude
这一定律最适合用于  数据范围跨越好几个数量级的情况
as they do for 3x+1.
就如 3x+1 一样
But Benford's law can't tell us
不过它并不能告诉我们
whether all numbers will end up in the four, two, one loop or not.
是不是所有数字都会落入 4-2-1 循环
For that, we need a different sort of analysis.
为此  我们需要用其他方法来分析
Now, at first glance, it seems strange that
乍一看  任意数字代进3x+1最终都得到1是蛮奇怪的
when you apply 3x+1, all numbers should end up at one.
I mean, consider that there are the same number of odd and even numbers,
我的意思是 考虑到奇数和偶数是一样多的
but odd numbers are more than tripled,
但奇数不止翻了两倍
while even numbers are only cut in half.
而偶数只减少了一半
Therefore, it seems like every sequence on average should grow, not shrink.
因此  平均来看  数列应该会趋向上升而非下降
But here's the catch.
但这就是问题所在
Every time you multiply an odd number by 3 and then add 1,
每当一个奇数×3+1
it will always become an even number,
它一定会变成偶数
and that means the next step is to divide by 2.
下一步它就会÷2
So odd numbers are not actually tripled by 3x+1.
所以奇数实际上不会因为3x+1变成原来的三倍
They're increased by a factor of about three over two.
它们会增长到原来的3/2
I'm neglecting the plus one
+1可以忽略
because it's insignificant for large numbers.
因为它对于大数是微不足道的
And 3/2 is actually the most an odd number can grow in one step.
而且 3/2 倍是奇数在一步之内能增长的最大值
Think of the path from one odd number in a sequence to the next odd number.
考虑3x+1数列中  由所有奇数组成的变化路径
After multiplying by 3 and adding 1, you have an even number.
奇数在×3+1之后  你就得到了偶数
And 50% of the time, dividing by 2 brings you back to an odd number.
有50%的可能  ÷2就能变回奇数
But 1/4 of the time, you can divide by 4 before you get to the next odd number.
但还有1/4的可能  要÷4才会变回奇数
So, for 1/4 of numbers, the next one in the sequence will be 3/4 of its initial value.
这种情况下  下面的红圈里的数会是上面的3/4
An 1/8 the time, you can divide by 8 before getting to the next odd number,
有1/8的可能  要÷8才会得到下一个奇数
and 1/16 of the time, you can divide by 16 and so on.
有1/16的可能  要÷16才行  以此类推
If you take the geometric mean, you find
算算几何平均数  可以发现
on average, to get from one odd number to the next one,
序列里的后一个奇数平均是前一个奇数的3/4倍  也就是平均会变小
you multiply by 3/4, which is less than one.
So statistically speaking, 3x+1 sequences are more likely to shrink than grow.
所以从统计学上讲  3x+1数列更倾向于收缩  而非增长
Take 341 for example,
用341做例子
multiply by three and add one, you get 1,024,
×3+1得到1024
which you can divide by two
你可以把它÷2
and then divide by two again, and again, and again, and again,
再÷2  再÷2  ÷2  ÷2…
10 times in total until you're down to one.
10步后会到达1
One way to visualize these paths of numbers in 3x+1
有种方法能形象地描述3x+1数列的路径
is simply to show how each number connects to the next one in its sequence.
就是把序列中每个相邻的数画条边连接
This is called a directed graph.
这就是所谓的「有向图」
It looks like a tree or a series of little streams that flow into each other.
它看起来像一棵树  或者是一大片逐渐汇聚的溪流
If the conjecture is true, it means that every single number is connected to this graph.
如果这个猜想成立  那就意味着所有的正整数都会连在这个图里
Every tiny stream all the way out to infinity
每条从1一直上溯至无穷的小溪流
eventually flows into the massive river of four, two, one.
最终都会汇入 4-2-1 的洪流
Some mathematicians have modified this visualization by rotating the graph at each number;
有些数学家换了种方法来描绘——把图里的每个数字转个角度
anticlockwise if it's an odd number,
如果是奇数  就逆时针转
and clockwise if it's even.
是偶数  就顺时针转
And then you end up with a structure that looks like a coral or seaweed.
最后你会得到一个看起来像珊瑚或者海草的结构
And by adjusting the degree of rotation for odd and even numbers,
通过改变奇数和偶数旋转的角度
you can create these beautiful, organic-looking shapes.
你可以创造出这些美丽的有机形状
Now, there are two ways the conjecture could be false.
要想推翻这个猜想  有两种方式
There could be a number somewhere, some seed,
可能有某个数的3x+1数列会一直增长到无穷
that starts a sequence of numbers that grows to infinity.
For whatever reason, it doesn't obey the same numerical gravity as all of the other numbers.
它出于某种原因  不会跟其他数一样落到1
Another possibility is there exists a sequence of numbers that forms a closed loop.
另一种可能是  存在一批会形成闭环的数
All the numbers in this loop would be unconnected to the main graph.
这个环中的所有数字跟主图不联通
But thus far, no loop or sequence that shoots off to infinity has been found.
但是目前为止  暂时没人找到有环或者能增长到无穷大的数列
And not for lack of trying, mathematicians have tested by brute force
数学家们可不是没试过  他们已经穷举了
every single number up to 2^68.
2的68次方以内的所有数
That's 295,147,905,179,352,825,856 numbers.
这是2垓9514京7905兆1793亿5282万5856个数
We know, for certain, that every single one of those numbers
我们能确定  这里面的任何一个数  最后都会落到1
eventually comes back down to one.
We have tested nearly 300 quintillion numbers,
我们测试了接近3万亿亿个数
and none of them disproves the conjecture.
没有一个反例
In fact, given this information,
事实上  依靠这些信息
mathematicians calculate that any loop other than 4, 2, 1
数学家得出  如果存在4-2-1以外的循环
must be at least 186 billion numbers long.
其至少应包含1860亿个数
So, it seems pretty likely that the conjecture is true,
所以  看起来这个猜想很像是成立的
but this doesn't prove it.
但这并不能证明它
One way mathematicians have attempted to prove it
数学家尝试证明它的一种方法
is by making a scatterplot,
是绘制散点图
with all the seed numbers on the x-axis
数列首项在X轴上
and a number from each seeds sequence on the y-axis.
数列中产生的数在Y轴上
Now, if you can show that in every 3x+1 sequence
现在  如果能证明每个3x+1数列中
there is a number that is smaller than the original seed,
都存在某项小于数列首项
well then you have proven the Collatz conjecture.
那就能证明考拉兹猜想
Because whatever number you pick,
因为无论你选择什么数
you know it will at some point get smaller,
你都知道它的数列中会有某项更小的
and that smaller number as a seed also gets smaller,
而这个更小的项能继续变得更小
and so on down to 1,
以此类推直至落到 1
meaning the only way any sequence can end is in the 4, 2, 1 loop.
意味着所有数列都会以 4-2-1 循环结尾
This has not yet been shown.
这还没有被证明
But, in 1976, Riho Terras was able to show that
但在1976年  Riho Terras证明了
almost all Collatz sequences reach a point below their initial value.
「几乎所有」考拉兹数列都存在小于其初值的数
In 1979, this limit was reduced with almost all numbers going to less than X^0.869.
1979年  上界缩小至「几乎所有」x 的数列都有数小于 x 的0.869次方
And then in 1994, it was further lowered to less than X^0.7925.
1994年  上界进一步缩小至 x 的0.7925次方
In this case, the term almost all numbers has a technical mathematical definition.
术语「几乎所有数」 是数学专门的定义
It means that as the numbers you're looking at go to infinity,
它的意思是  只要你要研究的数会一直趋向到无穷
the fraction that end up under the curve goes to one.
其比例会渐近趋向于1
Then in 2019,
2019年
one of the world's greatest living mathematicians,
目前在世的最伟大的数学家之一
Terry Tao,
陶哲轩
was able to show 3x+1 obeys even stricter criteria.
证明了3x+1数列还可以满足更严格的条件
He showed almost all numbers will end up smaller than any arbitrary function f(x)
他证明了  几乎所有数列的归宿  都会小于任意函数f(x)
so long as that function goes to infinity as x goes to infinity.
只要当x增长到无穷时  函数会随着增长到无穷
But the function can rise as slowly as you like.
但这个函数的增长速度可以任意慢
So, log x is an example, or log log log x works too,
这个函数可以是 log x   也可以是 log log log x
or log log log log x.
或是 log log log log x
What this means is, for almost all numbers, you can guarantee
这个结果的含义是  对几乎所有数  你都可以保证
that there is an arbitrarily small number somewhere in its sequence.
其数列中有一个比它任意小的数
In a public talk he gave in 2020, Terry Tao said,
2020年  陶哲轩在一次公开演讲中说
这个结果距离解答考拉兹猜想只差最后的关键一步了
This is an impressive result, but it's still not a proof.
这是个令人赞叹的结果  但依然不是证明
So why can't we prove the conjecture true?
所以我们为什么证明不了猜想成立呢
Could it be because it's not true?
有没有可能因为这是个假命题
I mean, everyone is trying to prove it true,
我的意思是  每个人都在试图证真
which means almost no one is looking for counterexamples.
换言之  几乎没有人在找反例
- It had happened to me just two years ago,
我两年前就碰到过
where there was something I was trying to prove,
那时我正在我证明一个  我尝试了三年的课题
that I was trying for three years to prove,
and I couldn't get it to work.
但我就是没法证明其正确性
And then I found a counterexample,
结果我找到了个反例
and then I realized what the correct statement should have been.
然后我意识到了正确的命题应该是怎样的
And then a month later, I proved the correct statement.
一个月后  我证明了那个正确的命题
Maybe we should be spending more energy
或许我们研究这些问题时  应该把更多精力放在寻找反例上
looking for counterexamples than we're currently spending.
- I mean, remember how the number 27 grows all the way to 9,232?
还记得27是如何增长到9232的吗
Here is a plot of seed numbers up to 10,000,
这个散点图包含了一万以下的所有初值
with the largest number reached for each seed plotted on the y-axis.
并在Y方向上标出了其3x+1数列中的最大值
The y-axis stops at a 100,000,
Y轴只标记到了十万
but not all numbers can be shown at this scale.
图中并没有将所有的最值都囊括在内
The seed 9,663, for example, climbs as high as 27 million.
比如说  初值为9663时  其最值会攀升至2700万
And as yet, no one has proven why a number couldn't just shoot off to infinity.
目前为止  没有人证明  为什么没有哪个初值会发散
And it would take only one to disprove the conjecture,
只要有一个反例  就能证伪这个猜想
or some set of numbers could be part of a loop not connected to the main graph.
或者存在某些数会形成与主图不相连的循环
As far as we know, there is only one loop: 4, 2, 1.
尽管我们现在只知道一个循环：4-2-1
But something strange happens if you include negative numbers.
Applying the same 3x+1 rules as before,
there is not one loop, not two loops,
but three independent loops of numbers.
And they start at low values like -17 and -5.
Why should there be disconnected loops on the negative side of the number line,
but not on the positive side?
Now, one of the most convincing pieces of evidence supporting the conjecture is
Terry Tao's proof that almost all numbers
have a number in their sequence that is arbitrarily small.
But proving that almost all numbers obey this criteria
isn't the same thing as proving that all numbers do.
How many numbers between one and 100 are perfect squares?
The answer is 10.
So, 10% of numbers up to 100 are perfect squares.
How many numbers between one and 1,000 are perfect squares?
The answer is 31.
So only 3.1% of the numbers up to 1,000 are perfect squares.
And the higher you go, the smaller this percentage becomes,
such that in the limit, you could say
almost all numbers are not perfect squares.
The fraction of numbers that are not perfect squares
goes to one as X goes to infinity.
And yet we know there are an infinite number of perfect squares
and we know exactly where they are.
Now, we've tested by brute force all numbers up to 2^68,
and they all obey the Collatz conjecture.
And you might be thinking that we should have found a counterexample by this point.
But on the scale of all numbers, 2^68 is nothing.
I mean, the Pólya conjecture proposed in 1919 by George Pólya
asserted that the majority of natural numbers
up to any given number have an odd number of prime factors.
The conjecture was eventually proven false
by C. Brian Haselgrove in 1958
when he identified a counterexample.
What's remarkable is the value of this counterexample
was 1.845×10^361.
That's some 10^340 times bigger
than all the numbers checked for 3x+1.
One way to think about 3x+1
is as though it's a simple program run on a Turing machine.
The seed number is the input to the machine.
So in this picture, 2^68 is simply an input tape 68 squares long.
You can think of them as a string of ones and zeros or black and white squares.
Saying the machine has transformed every input
up to this 68 square taped down to one
should not give you a lot of confidence that it will do so for all inputs.
In fact, it's fairly simple
to calculate a number that shows
any arbitrary behavior you like, so long as it is finite.
But if you want a number that increases by 3/2,
five consecutive times, you can calculate that number.
If you want a number that climbs by 3/2,
10 times in a row, or
100 times or 1,000 times,
you can easily calculate those numbers.
But after the finite section you specify,
you have no more control.
And every that has ever been tested, always falls to one.
If there is a counterexample, it's virtually impossible that someone's gonna guess it.
And the space of all possibilities is too big to search exhaustively by brute force.
2^1,000 is not a searchable space.
So, if we're gonna find it, we have to find it by some intelligent process
and not by guess and check.
I had been on team 3x+1 for 20 years.
And then this point of view,
I realized that, what do we really know?
It's very hard to prove a theorem that's false.
And so, could it be that everyone is struggling
to prove this thing because it's not actually true?
And 2^60 is not a lot of evidence.
And even the statistical version is maybe true and
not evidence for the non-existence of a divergent trajectory somewhere
in the 3x+1 sequence.
- Of course there is another option, and that is that we'll never know,
that the problem is undecidable.
In 1987, John Conway created a generalization of 3x+1.
It was a mathematical machine that he called FRACTRAN.
And he was able to show this machine is Turing-complete,
which means it can do anything a modern computer can do,
but it also means that it's subject to the halting problem,
a chance that the machine never stops running and so doesn't give you an output.
And this does not prove that 3x+1 is also subject to the halting problem,
but it is possible that given what we know,
we may never prove the Collatz conjecture true or false.
- You're gonna be taught in school that we know a bunch of stuff
and it's a lie. They're all lies.
Here's this stupid little problem.
Come on, really we can't solve this? Really?
You know, it just shows that math is hard.
If anything, it shows that all of the things that we can solve are miracles.
We have no right to have solutions to all of these other problems.
- For my whole life, I've thought of numbers as these incredibly regular things
full of patterns, symmetry, and repetition.
But what I'm realizing only now is just how peculiar numbers really are.
You can see this most clearly in the coral representation.
From a simple mathematical operation
comes something intricate, organic-looking, and, thus far, intractable to us.
Do all numbers connect to the structure?
Or is there some unique filament, a spindly little thread,
that doesn't connect to any of this, that runs off to infinity?
And why is it so hard to tell?
I think that's why Paul Erdős said,
"Mathematics is not yet ripe enough for such questions."